Guide to the Walt Whitman papers, 1841-1940, bulk 1841-1891 RL.01378
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1841-1891 and undated
  - Manuscript Prose, 1852-1891 and undated
    - Miscellany
      - "Produce great persons and the producers of great persons" (Volume 51)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written on one sheet of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches. Recto: twenty-four lines in pencil and ink, revised. Verso: two clippings, with annotations. In a board folder.
      - "The RR we go on (Sep 13 '79) from St Louis" "wooding at night—the 20 deck hands at work" (Volume 111)
        Description from Frey: Two autograph manuscripts: the first is written in pencil on eight sheets of paper, about 6x4 inches, one side only except for the last sheet; 116 lines. The second is written in pencil on two sheets of faded blue paper (three pages), about 9x7 inches; fifty-five lines. Bound in a quarto volume, half green morocco. A portion of a diary kept by Whitman on his trip from St. Louis to Colorado in 1879, and notes dealing with his journey home from New Orleans in 1848.
      - Specimen Days Oct 31 '84 Presidential Election" (Volume 46)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written on one sheet of ruled paper, about 12 x 8 inches. Recto: about twenty lines, written in purple pencil with additions in lead pencil. Verso: a rough draft of a letter, in pencil and much revised, from Whitman to Dion Thomas, "Washington Oct. 13." Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, green morocco back. A jotting intended for a new and expanded edition of Specimen Days; a newspaper clipping headed "A Poet in Politics" is pasted at the bottom of the sheet. In the letter, Whitman inquires about James Gray, the custodian of the sheets of Leaves of Grass.
      - "Sunday '79. —Took a slow walk forenoon to-day — (Easter-Sunday)" (Volume 112)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink and pencil on one sheet of paper, about 8x7 inches, one side only; twenty-four lines. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, orange morocco back. A diary jotting made near Central Park, New York City (Diary in Canada, pages 56-57). With a newspaper clipping describing Whitman's visit to New York in the spring of 1877.
      - "Theological inferences once thought orthodox may be demolished" (Volume 35)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on a scrap of paper, about 3x7 inches, one side only; ten lines, revised. A fragment dealing with the Bible and its importance to poets.
      - "visit to N Y '78 July 3" (Volume 119)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one side only of a sheet of ruled paper, about 8x5 inches, with the letterhead of the Pennsylvania House of Representatives on verso; twenty-six lines, revised in ink and pencil. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, white pigskin back. A diary jotting dealing with the view from the top of the tower of the Tribune building {Diary in Canada, page 55).
      - "[1863] Wednesday 4th March... Close of the 37th Congress —House (Volume 59)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in a small booklet of sixteen leaves, 5x4 inches, composed of eight sheets of ruled paper folded together and fastened at the fold by a pin; the writing, in ink and pencil, appears on the recto only of the first fourteen leaves and on both sides of the last two; about 160 lines. Laid in a full green morocco box case, gilt and blind tooled. Notes describing the adjournment of Congress in March, 1863 (partly published in Diary in Canada, pages 49-52).
      - "The Whale" (Volume 88)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of blue paper, about 11x4 inches, one side only; thirty-two lines, revised. In a board folder. Notes on the habits and characteristics of whales (Camden Edition, vi, 136-137).
      - "What are inextricable from the British poets are" (Volume 70)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on two sheets of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches. Recto: forty-four lines. Verso of second page: Whitman has pasted a clipping on Cowper on the sheet and has written above it, "Cowper 1731-1800 an ennuyeed poet." Bound in a royal octavo volume, cloth, green morocco back. A comment on the general nature of British poets (Camden Edition, vi, 114-116).
  - Proofs, 1874-1891 and undated
    Proofs of poems and articles published during Whitman's lifetime, some with autograph annotation by Whitman. The dates provided are taken both from the periodicals that carried corrected versions of the articles and poems in proof and also from autograph annotations to the proofs themselves. A mark of "P" next to a date indicates that the proof in question has been dated according to the periodical in which it appeared; a mark of "A," conversely, indicates that the proof has been dated by annotation. Where possible, the titles of the periodicals that published finalized versions of Whitman's articles and poems have been included. Listed alphabetically by title or periodical.
    - "Old Age's Lambent Peaks." "A Carol Closing Sixty-Nine." "To Get the Final Lilt of Songs, " undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy or offprint; in a board folder.
    - "Col. Ingersoll's Lecture—'Liberty and Literature.' Philadelphia, Oct. 21st, 1890." (A) (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy or offprint. With a clipping from the World (N. Y.), October 26, 1890, reporting a discussion between Ingersoll and Whitman. In a board folder.
    - "The Dead Carlyle." (P) (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy or offprint; endorsed by Whitman, "Boston Literary World Feb: 12— 1881." In a board folder.
    - "The Dead Tenor. From the Critic—New York, Nov. 8, '84." (P) (Box 10, Folder 5)
      Description from Frey: Offprint; in a board folder.
    - "Death of a Fireman. From the New Republic, Camden, N. J. Nov. 14th. '74." (P) (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Halcyon Days," undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy, with minor corrections, presumably by Whitman. In a board folder.
    - "Have We a National Literature? From the North American Review, March, 1891." (P) (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Description from Frey: Offprint, four pieces. In a board folder.
    - "A Memorandum at a Venture. From the North American Review." (A) (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Description from Frey: Offprint; in a board folder. Another copy, clipped into four pieces. Endorsed by R. M. Bucke, "For June 1882." In a board folder.
    - November Boughs, undated (Volume 207)
      Description from Frey: Page proofs, pages 5-1 40, with frontispiece. Wrapped in a sheet of paper, inscribed: "Proof slips —sent me as struck off by W. W.—of November Boughs RMB." With a review of November Boughs, clipped from the Chicago Daily News, February 9, 1889, endorsed in Whitman's autograph. In a half green morocco slipcase.
    - "Of That Blithe Throat of Thine." (P) (Box 10, Folder 10)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy or offprint; endorsed by Whitman, "From January Harpers." In a board folder.
    - "Patroling Barnegat." (A) (Box 10, Folder 11)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy or offprint. Endorsed by R. M. Bucke: "Unpublished—private. Received from Walt June 3, 1880." In a board folder.
    - "Preface," undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy or offprint. Endorsed by R. M. Bucke: "Reached me from W. W. 27th Sept. in letter dated 24th & 25th Sept RMB." In a board folder. Preface to Three Tales by W. D. O'Connor.
    - "Shakespeare for America. From the Poet-Lore, September 15, 1890." (P) (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "Summer Days in Canada." (P) (Box 15)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy, two pieces; dated June 19, to which Bucke has added " '80." With a clipping of the article from the London Advertiser, June 22, 1880. In a board folder. Also, a duplicate of the second piece of this proof copy, begin ning with the sub-heading, "Sunday with the Insane." With one correction, presumably by Whitman. In a board folder.
    - Sunday with the Insane, London Advertiser, 1890 June 22 (P) (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - "Thanks in Old Age," undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy, with several corrections in Whitman's autograph.
    - "To the Sun-Set Breeze," undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - "A Twilight Song." (P) (Box 10, Folder 17)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy; endorsed by Whitman: "Century N Y May 1890."
    - "Walt Whitman. The True Reminiscence of his Writings. From the 'West Jersey Press,' May 24th, 1876." (P) (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - "Walt Whitman's Actual American Position. From the West Jersey Press, Jan. 26th, 1876." (P) (Box 10, Folder 19)
      Description from Frey: Offprint; in a board folder. Two copies.
    - "With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!" (A) (Box 10, Folder 20)
      Description from Frey: Offprint. Endorsed by R. M. Bucke: "Given me by W. W. Nov 1883 before it was published —First pubd Harper's Mthly March 1884." In a board folder.
    - "Your kind invitation to visit you and deliver a poem for the 333d Anniversary of founding Santa Fe, " undated (Box 10, Folder 21)
      Description from Frey: Proof copy, with a few minor corrections, presumably by Whitman. In a board folder.
  - Periodicals Containing Contributions by Whitman, 1841-1891
    Periodicals containing poems, essays, and letters contributed by Whitman. Listed alphabetically by periodical or book title.
    - Periodicals
      - Atlantic Monthly
        - No. 30: Bardic Symbols, pp. 445-7, 1860 Apr. (Box 13)
      - The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine
        - Vol. XXXIX, no. 4: Old Age's Ship and Crafty Death, p. 553, 1890 Feb. (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - The Democratic Review
        - Vol. XL, No. LI: The Angel of Tears, p. 282, 1842 Sept. (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - The Galaxy
        - Vol. IV, no. 5: A Card of Harvest for 1867, pp. 605-9, 1867 Sept.
        - Vol. XI: O Star of France!, p. 817, 1871 Jan.-July
      - Harper's New Monthly Magazine
        - Vol. LXX, no. 416: Of That Blithe Throat of Thine, p. 64, 1885 Jan. (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Life Illustrated
        - Vol. I, no. 13: Christmas at Grace, p. 97, 1856 Jan. 26 (Box 14)
        - Vol. I, no. 24: America's Mightiest Inheritance, pp. 185-6, 1856 Apr. 2 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 2: Voltaire, p. 9, 1856 May 10 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 3: Fanny Fern's Opinion of Walt Whitman, pp. 20-1, 1856 May 17 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 11: New York Dissected, part 1, p. 85, 1856 July 12 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 12: New York Dissected, part 2, p. 93, 1856 July 19 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 14: New York Dissected, part 3, pp. 108-9, 1856 Aug. 2 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 15: New York Dissected, part 4, p. 116, 1856 Aug. 9 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 16: New York Dissected, part 5, p. 125, 1856 Aug. 16 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 17: New York Dissected, part 6, p. 133, 1856 Aug. 23 (Box 14)
        - Vol. II, no. 22: Advertisement for second edition of Leaves of Grass, 1856 Sept. 27 (Box 14)
      - Lippincott's Monthly Magazine
        - Vol. XXXIX, no. 229: My Book and I, pp. 121-7, 1887 Jan. (Box 13, Folder 4)
        - pp. 376-388, 1891 Mar. (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - The New World
        - Extra Series, no. 34: Franklin Evans; or, the Inebriate. A Tale of the Times, pp. 1-31, 1842 Nov. (Box 14)
      - The North American Review
        - The Poetry of the Future, 1881 Feb. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - The Northern Pioneer
        - Vol. I, no. 15: Wild Frank's Return, p. 116, 1848 Oct. 7 (Box 15)
      - The Portland (Me.) Transcript
        - Vol. XIV, no. 19: Resurgemus, p. 148, 1850 Aug. 24 (Box 15)
        - Vol. XXIII, no. 43: You and Me and Today, p. 342, 1860 Jan. 28 (Box 15)
      - Transactions of the Buffalo Historical Society
        - Vol. III: Red Jacket, (From Aloft), p. 105, 1885
      - The United States Magazine and Democratic Review
        - NS Vol. IX, no. 38: Death in the School-Room. A Fact, pp. 177-81, 1841 Aug.
          See: http://search.library.duke.edu/search?id=DUKE000345779
        - NS Vol. IX, no. 41: Wild Frank's Return, pp. 476-82, 1841 Nov.
        - NS Vol. IX, no. 42: Bervance: or, Father and Son, pp. 560-8, 1841 Dec.
        - NS Vol. X, no. 43: The Tomb-Blossoms, pp. 62-8, 1842 Jan.
        - NS Vol. X, no. 47: The Child-Ghost; A Story of the Last Loyalist, pp. 451-9, 1842 May
        - Vol. XVII, no. 89: A Dialogue, pp. 360-4, 1845 Nov.
- Clippings, 1845-1891 and undated, bulk 1845-1855
  This series consists of two groups: large collections of clippings (listed first), and clippings of individual articles. The former are listed by the heading given each collection in Frey and the contents are described. The latter are listed alphabetically by article title and are further identified by periodical or anthology and date.
  - Magazine Articles and Clippings (Volume 223)
    Description from Frey: The collection, apparently made by Whitman, begins with seven pieces of paper, on which are written about seventy lines, in pencil and ink, chiefly lists of titles of magazine articles and names of famous authors. On these pages also are mounted clippings dealing with the following subjects: the ills of mankind; the poetry of Gerald Massey; "Bookmaking in the United States" (Life Illustrated, n.s., ii (May 31, 1856), 35); "Newspapers in the World"; "Literature and the Book Trade in the United States"; "Fast Printing Again"; the reply of a Mr. Burke to the toast of the "Poets of Ireland" (endorsed, "Brooklyn Eagle March 18 '57"); "Hume's Philosophy"; "Oliver Goldsmith." A group of magazine excerpts follows: a portion of "Lessing's Laocoon," by J. D. Whelpley, American Whig Review, n.s., vii (January, 1851), 21-26; a portion of "Nationality in Literature," United States Democratic Review, xx (March, 1847), 265-272; "Poems of Alfred Tennyson," Westminster Review, American edition, li (July, 1849), 145-156; "The Poets and Poetry of Europe," American Whig Review, iv (December, 1846), 581-588; "The Mississippi Valley," United States Democratic Review, xx (May, 1847), 417-424; "The Laws of Menu," by J. D. Whelpley, American Whig Review, 1 (May, 1845), 509-522; "Writings of Cornelius Mathews," pages 169-184, clipped from W. G. Simms's Views and Reviews, Second Series; "Channing," a brief sketch from Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1, 166-167; "Constantinople in the Fourth Century," Littell's Living Age, xi (November 28, 1846), 427-430; "Niebuhr," North British Review, American edition, x (February, 1849), 179-188; "[Dies Boreales. No. in.] Christopher Under Canvass," Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine, lxvi (August, 1849), 237-262; "Earthquakes in New Zealand," Westminster Review, American edition, li (July, 1849), 207-218; "Johnston's Physical Atlas," North British Review, American edition, ix (August, 1848), 195-202; "Jean-Charles-Leonard de Sismondi," United States Democratic Review, xx (April, 1847), 305-3I6; "Indian Mounds," Merchants' Magazine and Commercial Review, xv (November, 1846), 479-482; W. G. Simms, ibid., pages 143-146; "Ancient Practice of Painting," Blackwood's, lxv (April, 1849), 435-452, "Philosophy, Psychology, and Metaphysics," Eclectic Magazine, n.s., xiii (April, 1871), 385-400; "Architecture," Westminster Review, American edition, li (April, 1849), 55-66, the first paragraphs of an article on the "Scotch School of Philosophy and Criticism," American Whig Review, ii (October, 1845), 386; a clipping on Roman virtue; "Crabbe," a brief sketch, Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1, 113-114; "Civilization," by Guizot, Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1, 119-128; a clipping on a lecture on Cowper, mounted upon a page from a review of Beattie's Life and Letters of Thomas Campbell, Quarterly Review, American edition, lxxxv (July, 1849), 17-18; "Scotch School of Philosophy and Criticism," American Whig Review, ii (October, 1845), 387-396; "The 'Hyperion' of Keats," by J. D. Whelpley, American Whig Review, n.s., viii (October, 1851), 317-322; selections from early English poetry, clipped from an anthology, pages 17-20, 27-28, 37-38; "Froissart," Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1, ii; Johnson's essay on Shakespeare, clipped from an anthology, pages 322-330; Jefferson's character of Washington and an anonymous sketch of Napoleon, Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1, 474-480; an article on Victor Hugo, Sartain's Magazine, v (December, 1849), 334-335, a portion of Hume's "On the Jealousy of Trade," Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1, 86-88; "Hungary," Westminster Review, American edition, li (July, 1849), 223-250; "List of Patents Issued... for the week ending May 12, 1857"; "Mrs. Somerville's Physical Geography," North British Review, American edition, ix (May, 1848), 75-100; "Robert Burns," Life Illustrated, N.s., iv (July 18, 1857), 89. With annotations by Whitman. Bound in a royal octavo volume, half blue morocco.
  - Magazine Articles and Clippings (Volume 186)
    Description from Frey: A group of seventeen items, as follows: Robert Chambers, "Present State of the British Empire," pages 671-680 from an anthology; "Raleigh's History," a clipping; "Imagination and Fact," Graham's Magazine, xl (January, 1852), 39-44, an article, with a clipping on the seven wonders of the world pasted on page 39; "The Slavonians and Eastern Europe," North British Review, American edition, xi (August, 1849), 283-306, a review of several works on Slavonic peoples; a clipping on Pindar, with a translation of the Twelfth Olympic Ode; a clipping on contemporary Russian literature, "N. Y. Tribune of March 26 '57"; a clipping, "The Winds," by W. C. Bryant; an article on iron ships, "N. Y. Times '57"; a newspaper clipping on an ancient Persian inscription; "Fourier and his Ideas," a clipping from the Tribune, April, 1857; four brief clippings, "Books Mentioned in the Bible Now Lost or Unknown," "Chevalier Bunsen's Chronology," "The Discovery of America" (by Buddhist priests in 459 A. D.), and an estimate of the world's population, divided by religions, from the "Herald, Feb. 13, '60"; two clippings, "Carrying the Mails to California," and a portion of an article on keel-boatmen. With annotations by Whitman. In a small quarto volume, boards.
  - Twenty-Nine Newspaper and Magazine Items (Volume 188)
    Description from Frey: Clippings, as follows: "Nicknames of European Nations," endorsed "Lippincott's Feb: '91"; "Plato"; "From Rome," Correspondence of the New York Tribune, Rome, March 24, 1857; "How a Poet Eats Planked Shad at Gloucester," endorsed "Camden Post May 6 1884"; "Dr. Charles Mackay, on English Songs and Song- Writers"; "Death of the French Tennyson," endorsed "Tribune June '57"; a note on a book, The Shakespeare Problem Solved, by Delia Bacon, endorsed "April '57"; "Remittances to the Old Country," endorsed "Feb. '54"; a paragraph clipped from Whitman's "A Christmas Garland" {Christmas Graphic, 1874); a portion of Whitman's "An Indian Bureau Reminiscence," clipped from Baldwin's Monthly, xxviii (February, 1884); "Ascent of Mount Popocatapetl," endorsed "Tribune March 23d '54"; "The Amazon Basin," endorsed "Herald March 19 '54"; "Interesting Slave Trial," endorsed "March 1854"; "Facts from History," endorsed "Tribune, March 27 '54"; "Death of Hugh Millar," endorsed "N. Y. Sun, Jan. 13, '57"; "Records of Mortality. Mr. Josiah D. Bangs," endorsed "Sept. 1856"; "Grand Exhibition of the Brooklyn Horticultural Society," Brooklyn Daily Eagle, September 20, 1856; "Death of Eugene Sue," endorsed " '57"; "An Enormous Ape"; "The Ages of Foreign Living Writers," endorsed "Jan. 1860" and mounted on the first page of an article by Henry Tuckerman, "Petrarch," American Whig Review, 1 (May, 1845), 468; "From John Burroughs' notes, 1872," portion of a review of Burroughs' Notes on Walt Whitman, heading supplied by Whitman; "Walt Whitman's Impressions of Denver and the West," endorsed "From the Denver (Colorado) Tribune Sept: 12 1879"; "A Poet's Western Visit," endorsed "From the Washington Evening Star Nov: 15 1879"; "A Week at West Hills. Letter from Walt Whitman," New York Tribune, August 4, 1881; "Walt Whitman. A Poet's Supper to his Printers and Proof Readers," endorsed "Camden Post Oct 18 '81"; "City Notes in August. Letter from Walt Whitman," Tribune, August 15, 1881; "Sea Isle City," Camden Post, July 9, 1886; obituary notice of David Stuart of Detroit, endorsed "Tribune Oct. 22, 1853." With annotations by Whitman. Mounted in a quarto volume, cloth.
  - Notes and Clippings, Chiefly on Eastern Poetry (Volume 158)
    Description from Frey: Lorenzo D. Johnson, Memoria Technica, pages 83-86, on the first of which is mounted a clipping headed "Persian Secretaries"; "The Golden Verses of Pythagoras," a translation, pages 207-214 from an anthology; a sheet of pink paper on which are mounted two clippings, one on Siamese proverbs and literature, the other on the "Absurd Chronology of the Hindoos." With several annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - Clippings on the Wreck of the San Francisco (Box 16)
    Description from Frey: Six clippings, from the New York Tribune of January and February, 1854, dealing chiefly with the wreck of the steamer San Francisco; with two annotations by Whitman. In a board folder.
  - "Anacreon" (Volume 151)
    Description from Frey: A passage on Anacreon, with translations of several of his poems, pages 236-242 from Thoreau's A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers. Between pages 238 and 239 a clipping is inserted, a review of The Satires of Juvenal and Pershts, edited by Charles Anthon. In a board folder.
  - "Arnold's Lectures on Modern History" (Volume 177)
    Description from Frey: United States Democratic Review, xvii (October, 1845), 247-256. A review, with two annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Chaucer" (Volume 178)
    Description from Frey: North British Review, American edition, x (February, 1849), 157-178. A review of several editions of Chaucer, with numerous annotations by Whitman. On page 157 are mounted two dippings, on "Chinese Popular Literature" and on Scandinavian funeral customs; on page 178, four clippings with a manuscript heading: "Contemporaneous Literats. American & English." Bound in a royal octavo volume, half white pigskin.
  - "[Dies Boreales. No. 1.] Christopher Under Canvass" (Volume 179)
    Description from Frey: Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine, lxv (June, 1849), 763-766. A portion of a literary discussion, dealing in these pages chiefly with Milton, Homer, and Wordsworth; extensively annotated by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, half white pigskin.
  - "Early Roman History" (Volume 185)
    Description from Frey: Western Review, 1 (April, 1846), 211-274. A review of Arnold's and Niebuhr's histories of Rome, with numerous annotations by Whitman. In a board folder.
  - "Egotism. As Manifested in the Works and Lives of Great and Small Men" (Volume 180)
    Description from Frey: Graham's Magazine, xxvii (March, 1845), 97-103. An article, with several annotations by Whitman. A clipping consisting of a comment made by Aubrey on Dr. William Harvey is pasted on page 97. Three clippings, on Hume, Swift, and Addison, from Half-Hours with the Best Authors (1, 86, 116, 75-76) are mounted on page 103. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Excerpts (Box 16)
    Description from Frey: Five scraps of manuscript, thirty-six lines in all, followed by a series of forty-eight newspaper clippings and magazine excerpts, with annotations by Whitman. The collection as a whole deals with the tramp and strike problems in the United States. Mounted in a folio volume, cloth, orange morocco back.
  - "The French Moralists" (Volume 152)